{"tossups": [{"question": "This country\u2019s national language was transcribed by the Sorabe alphabet, which was inspired by Arabic and probably developed through contact with Omani traders. Jean Laborde served as an engineer for a monarch of this country, Ranavalona I, by building modern foundries for the Merina Kingdom. Malagasy is spoken in, for the point, what former French colony governed from Antananarivo, an island off the southeast coast of Africa?", "answer": "<b> Madagascar</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "In one work, a young woman from this country moves to the United States to reunite with Obinze, but instead becomes a real estate mogul. That book,<em> Americanah</em>, is a sequel to<em> Half of a Yellow Sun</em>, which takes place during this country\u2019s Biafran War. Another author from this country attacked the\u201cthoroughgoing racist\u201d Joseph Conrad in<em> An Image of Africa</em>. For the point, name this home country of the author of<em> Things Fall Apart</em>, Igbo writer Chinua Achebe [ah-chay-bay].", "answer": "Republic of<b> Nigeria</b>", "metadata": "Literature - World Literature - Long Fiction"}, {}, {"question": "In an opera set in this country, the namesake courtesan murders Dr. Ludwig Schon, flees to London, and is murdered herself by Jack the Ripper. That opera,<em> Lulu</em>, was composed by Alban Berg, a 20th century composer from this country who worked with 12-tone pioneer Arnold Schoenberg in the \u201cSecond\u201dmusical school named for its capital. For the point, name this country where Johann Strauss composed the \u201cBlue Danube\u201d waltz and \u201cTales from the Vienna Woods.\u201d", "answer": "<b> Austria</b> (accept<b> Austria-Hungary</b>; do not accept or prompt on Hungary alone)", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Auditory Fine Arts"}, {}, {}, {"question": "A president of this nation worked in conjunction with the US in Project Sapphire, allowing this nation to dismantle nuclear arms. Nikita Khrushchev\u2019s Virgin Lands Reforms hoped to turn pastoral lands in this modern-day nation into wheat producing lands. This former Soviet republic is the site of the Baikonur Cosmodrome, which is leased by neighboring Russia. For the point, name this Central Asian nation that, in 2019, honored former president Nursultan Nazarbayev by renaming its capital to Nur-Sultan from Astana.", "answer": "<b> Kazakhstan</b>", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {"question": "One version of this game has three tracks, with Music C simply being Bach\u2019s French Suite Number 3 in B minor. A 1993 photo of First Lady Hillary Clinton shows her playing this game on Air Force One. Alexey Pajitnov was initially not able to monetize this game because he lived in the USSR, but Russia reverted royalty rights to him in 1996. This game was bundled with the original Game Boy, making it one of the best-selling games of all time. For the point, name this classic puzzle game in which four-square blocks fall from the top of the screen.", "answer": "<b> Tetris</b>", "metadata": "Trash - Trash"}, {}, {"question": "One of these animals named Whistlejacket is the subject of a George Stubbs painting in the National Gallery. Anthony van Dyck\u2019s painting<em> Charles I at the Hunt</em> shows the British king resting to the left of one of these animals. Theodore Gericault showed several of these animals in a painting of an annual event held at Epsom. For the point, name these animals featured in paintings of the Derby and in equestrian portraits.", "answer": "<b> horse</b>s", "metadata": "Fine Arts - Visual Fine Arts"}, {}, {"question": "According to legend, at this event, Joseph Stalin found the proto-meme \u201cKilroy Was Here\u201d graffitied in a bathroom. At this event, Stalin requested to be given the Kuril Islands and promised that he would invade Japan three months after the fall of Germany. The Allies agreed to split Germany into four occupation zones at, for the point, what conference of Stalin, Roosevelt, and Churchill, held in February 1945 at a Crimean resort town?", "answer": "<b> Yalta</b> Conference", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "A leader of this empire altered the<em> khutba</em> daily prayer and was temporarily supplanted by Jahander Shah. The Maratha Confederacy seized its independence from this empire in 1674. The founder of this empire defeated Ibrahim Lodi at First Battle of Panipat. A leader of this empire constructed the Taj Mahal as a mausoleum for his wife. Babur, Akbar, and Shah Jahan were leaders of, for the point, what Indian empire?", "answer": "<b> Mughal</b> Empire (accept<b> Mogul</b> Empire)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {}, {}, {"question": "The northeastern part of this state was originally part of the Connecticut Western Reserve. In this state, Mad Anthony Wayne defeated a Shawnee-Miami alliance at the 1794 Battle of Fallen Timbers. This state fought its northern neighbor in the largely bloodless Toledo War. During the War of 1812, Oliver Hazard Perry defeated a British fleet off the coast of this state at the Battle of Lake Erie. For the point, name this Midwestern state explored by Moses Cleveland.", "answer": "<b> Ohio</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "With Pierre-Etienne Flandin and Ramsay MacDonald, this man reaffirmed the Locarno Treaties in the Stresa Front. After being rescued in the Gran Sasso raid, this man was made leader of the Republic of Salo. This man and his mistress were murdered by partisans and hanged upside down at an Esso gas station. In 1922, this man, supported by the Blackshirts, led a March on Rome. For the point, name this dictator who led Italy through World War II.", "answer": "Benito<b> Mussolini</b>", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {}, {"question": "This country signed the Haavara Agreement which allowed Jews to emigrate to Mandatory Palestine. In this country, insurance companies paid the government instead of afflicted parties after a series of attacks on homes and businesses called the Night of Broken Glass. This country was the site of the Wannsee Conference, where politicians discussed the Final Solution to the Jewish question. For the point, name this European country that was led by the Nazi party.", "answer": "Nazi<b> Germany</b>", "metadata": "Current Events - Current Events"}, {"question": "After being tipped off by Mosby Shepherd, this politician stopped Gabriel Prosser from carrying out his planned slave revolt. During this man\u2019s presidency, Maine joined the Union as a free state as part of the Missouri Compromise. This president\u2019s Secretary of State, John Quincy Adams, drafted a doctrine that opposed European intervention in the Americas. The \u201cEra of Good Feelings\u201d was ushered in by, for the point, what fifth President of the United States?", "answer": "James<b> Monroe</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {"question": "In this modern-day country, the Japanese trained the \u201cThirty Comrades\u201d to fight against colonial rule. The Allies used a \u201croad\u201d in this country to deliver supplies to the Second United Front during the Second Sino-Japanese War. In 1942, a Japanese invasion of this country forced British troops to retreat to neighboring India after the fall of Rangoon. For the point, name this Southeast Asian nation formerly known as Burma.", "answer": "<b> Myanmar</b> (accept<b> Burma</b> before it is read)", "metadata": "History - World History"}, {"question": "The namesake of this body of water was set adrift and presumed dead following a mutiny that occurred after he spent the winter of 1610 in nearby James Bay. This body of water lends its name to a fur trading company that today survives as a department store. For the point, name this large bay in northern Canada named for an English explorer.", "answer": "<b> Hudson</b> Bay", "metadata": "Geography - Geography"}, {"question": "For the point, name this \u201cGreat\u201dEmpress of Russia.", "answer": "<b> Catherine</b> the Great (accept<b> Catherine</b> II)", "metadata": "History - European History"}, {"question": "In the aftermath of this case, the Supreme Court was forced to reaffirm judicial supremacy in<em> Cooper</em> <em>v. Aaron</em>. The Gray Commission discovered that the orders handed down in this case had not been carried out. Thurgood Marshall represented the plaintiffs in this case, who had been unable to register their daughter for the school closest to their home.<em> Plessy v. Ferguson</em> was overturned by, for the point, what 1954 Supreme Court case that desegregated public schools?", "answer": "<b> Brown</b> v. Board of Education of Topeka, et al", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During this man\u2019s Presidency, Oakes Ames was caught overcharging the Union Pacific Railroad as part of the Credit Mobilier scandal. This man\u2019s Vice President, Schuyler Colfax, resigned due to scandal, causing him to be replaced by Henry Wilson. Orville Babcock, this man\u2019s personal secretary, was complicit in the tax-evading Whiskey Ring. For the point, name this 18th President of the United States, a former Civil War general.", "answer": "Ulysses S.<b> Grant</b>", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "During this conflict, the Lenape were given one thousand pesos in exchange for land in New Jersey as part of the Treaty of Easton. One side in this war launched the disastrous Braddock expedition, which failed to capture Fort Duquesne [doo-CANE]. James Wolfe died at the Plains of Abraham during this war while attempting to capture Quebec. For the point, name this North American extension of the Seven Years\u201d War, fought between Britain and its European rival.", "answer": "<b> French and Indian</b> War (prompt on Seven Years\u201d War before it is read)", "metadata": "History - American History"}, {}, {"question": "This government\u2019s navy was permanently crippled after an attack on its fleet at Mers-el-Kebir. Citizens under this government were targeted in the Vel d\u2019Hiv [vell deev] roundup, which transported them to the Winter Velodrome under the orders of Pierre Laval. In order to garner support, this government appointed the hero of Verdun, Philippe Petain, as its Prime Minister. For the point, name this puppet government of France that collaborated with the Nazis during World War II.", "answer": "<b> Vichy</b> France", "metadata": "History - European History"}], "bonuses": []}